Ever real treat...today
...we're bringing somebody out from under hiding and letting him
talked publicly he's been missing in action for five years.
This is my friend...box distinguish distinguished engineer
at microsoft hello dawn moi I'm...you it's
...nice to see you again after five years it's fantastic...well thank you thanks so I just
...start this by having you explain where the heck of you...five yearsso,
I've...busily products okay I just it's funny
I've given a couple toxin last month and,
I was up on stage in china and I realized with
...I've done this like five years, yeah, so, I've been pretty busy I would say
...the last five years...an interesting journeyI went to work xbox.
Come in two thousand and beginning to...and,
at the time...very of focus on building xbox one right so,
it was a very secret...there...no public,
you know, engagement whatsoever actually want to...a couple talks but they were in the
...okay so, we should xbox one and,
I went to go work it was jeep on the broader os and, you know, kind of,
you know, we work on the windows ten thing finally
...story this calendar year and that's what kind of
...yep...I have to...little story because my job is
I'm a reporter...done went to the xbox team I knew you went to the
xbox team and a lot of us who are watching microsoft...the...speculating what
...doing on the xbox team like here's a guy who's been working on things like
declarative programming languages and all that kinda stuff and suddenly he's on that,
yeah, it was definitely a bit of a non secular you know,...was on this project called oslo
positive wound down and I kind of...the earth microsoft
...next...your for rousing really and raised we had this project called
...which is a tv...became part of xbox.
...then we...up, you know, doing smart last-minute xbox one and,
it was really just, you know, it was about, you know, meeting ray ozzie was a big deal
any walter was great so there...these people want to work with...and,
I follow the people as opposed to what part of the way I found out what you're doing is I looked up your linkedin
And, there were some things on there that was good it was helpful I but now you have a title besides
distinguished engineer that's kind of complex...silicon right and, yeah,
so, graphics pptx...so
...xbox one I was the deb manager for the os platform so we do everything from
colonel silicon graphics media everything and, then, you know,
when we kind of change the way we're building operating systems I wound up actually I was
happy to become the guy who...in charge of all of the silicon graphics and
media for all products so what does that mean actually what do you do in
...and that rollers...what mighty does iswe deliver the graphics...I direct
...request twelve is obviously big initiative price we deliver that on all the products
...we do that on...on
phones on xbox on poland's on t skews on
...we also the media stacks all the audio basically if you can see it or hear it
someone of my team made it happen...because all the all of the visual...audio up
on the box go through my team and then all just the...silicon stuff whenever,
you know, intel qualcomm or silicon vendor has new piece of silicon someone's got to do
...bring up right and that's...does...kind of like a generalization what we did
an xbox we had exactly one piece of silicon exactly one product we...bill this
one this projects actually much more it much more complex simply because we're bouncing
multiple silicon bring...multiple prores...so, that's what that's...
How much you involved and what we've heard a lot here at buildabout which is universal
...platform...how does that play in with what you guys
well so it's a huge part of my job one of the things I'm responsible for
...of driving the component is a shun and structuring the operating system to make sure we can satisfy
all these products if you look at how we built windows
phony and xbox one when we originally built them you had
a different groups doing very isolated partitioning of
the operating system so if you look at the subset of windows the chips and windows phone...you'll get the
subset of windows chips on xbox one there's a lot of overlap but there's a lot of,
you know, somewhat different decisions and one of the things, you know,
I wanted to do...we set up...was I wanted to make sure that we could do
...structured way in a way that would help everybody right because it is we saw things like,
you know, athens which is the ot addition if we'll get...you know, we were about to,
you know, explode the combinatorially of the ways we combine,
... the windows code base so yeah, so, what we do is we basically, you know, at
the beginning of the project you can help...all the cards on the table to all the product where to go build
...kind of figure out how to strata by the os in such a way that we would have a predictable it's
a platform...span all of these devices here, you know,
here at this conference one of the biggest announcements was around ios
and android developers and how microsoft's trying to bring...
the platform yes how is that going to change what constitutes the common core
...the comment underlying platform is a committing generalI don't I don't know that has
...a deep impact on the...platform in the core platform...to go
...fact we're able to go run android...ios code is a virtue of the fact
...platforms pretty general-purpose right so I don't know that, you know,
there's a lot of deep changes were making the os that the...everyone
else we're absolutely committed to go to make those code...worthwhile on windows
I think in terms of the general way the system works, you know,...our apply?
I wish we had a surface hub right here because remember
...used...always draw these amazing architectural diagrams to explain things and, I am
...still get my head around the idea of with this common core and
common store and all of where...these new layers look like right so I know there's
...universal platform...platform layer is also universal driver framework
freight where...also...help fundamentally we have a bunch of operating system code
...we...right and it has a surface area that...iso...which is the app platform
right it has the surface area that's exposed to I interviews and silicon vendors which is the driver
...device platform it's the same product yet it's all we have two different platforms and we have
windows in many ways windows...of what windows and
has been about is coming up with a way to think about our code base of product
Such that we have a consistent platform for...for app developers
regain developer yet and consistent platform for device makers...
And, silicon vendors so it's really a manifestation about we were
constructing operating system.
...that helps...does it does...kind of thinking back and, showing my age here a
little on this but I remember when you guys are building windows seven and the whole idea about
...and how you guys return at de-couple things are all kind of...windows and,
make it kind of make more sense right separate things out you could basically set up for
what you're doing now I'm curious how you feel that's involved and honest
I would say windows...is the next natural step in the evolution like if you
win-win was ages ago what's right and it was the first stab I think we took
a kind of strata find the operating system and, coming up with more discipline about dependency management
...layering write each iteration we've done more of that certainly
...we build xbox one right we benefited from a lot of the evolution that work which
...time it was called core system right and, we certainly built on top of that
...came up with our own partitioning as did the phones and really if I look at windows
ten it's the generalization of that next...
right that actually is a layering that makes sense for all of these points...a single way to go
...the runs on all of these devices...love to talk about so it it's a natural evolution?
...with xbox one though at some point you're going to bring when windows tend
to that platform of someway right you say anything about that right now
...to be clear...I think we've been pretty open about it we run
...windows...right so if you're playing, you know, your xbox one there's
a copy windows in fact we run three operating systems on that box but the one that, you know,
kind of people focus on is the system os was where the shell runs through all the optron
...where a lot of system services run that is based on a snapple windows...that we
took back in two thousand twelve right and when the process of course
...that code base into windows...and,
we're making good progress on it and, you know,
it's very promising...excited and the promise of being able to do it is
we'll have the same code base the same api surface
...same behavior across xbox as well as you so isn't oversimplified to
There might be a case where somebody wants to run
and enterprise app on xbox and they would do it I mean
another things you could do versus what makes sense right well I mean it it's
a great question if we're talking about existing enterprise al-zoubi road...forms are divinity
...any the,... technologies will know for enterprise on the answer is that's
Like...get when we talk about strata for the operating system what we did for windows
ten we identify the line of shared functionality...components...and
...that...sense on every single device right and that did not
include all the things it takes to go run enterprise apps write those things like the things it takes
...make wpf...certainly ship on the
desktop skews but the only playstation just like there's things...only ship on the phone
right additions and...will be things that ownership on the xbox additional so you know,
really if you look at the app platform as we talk about it and you spend a lot of
...that is the shared but right absent target that platform are the ones will run.
That's stated there's a lot of things...pc's that are getting continue to...pcs thank
...writing for...
I've been watching a couple of recent keynote city did you did like you said one
...up...and you also...forget which one it was one of them
you talked about the microsoft corrupt.
You share a little more than.
I needed analogy I was talking about, you know,
this gratification the...and effective...this...that is that we deploy to all these different
...right and I was saying I and spontaneously aidid and plus
...I thought, you know, shoulder pads...just...would probably not
...appropriate for that talk maybe not quite helping...and I said I know of
...project that is a microsoft...really real...honest
engine moi stack of bibles I was sitting there watching your talk
and also I was going to...sitting at one point and I heard microsoft love and I'm like...just and now
...microsoft realizes soon as I said that it's entirely possible there is a microsoft
...you milford...you...and
...what you're saying those like innovate impala...right because they're all these other devices
your building this common platform for even some that aren't even built yet that it's
...yes so, yeah, I thought it was funny though because I started immediately searching for the
club I have found
...if you find the microsoft love I will sign it for-you okay...a
picture with you with I would love nothing more than to have a microsoft but I know of...okay I'm still kind of
curious about this xbox move that you made in your career the ships
...the xbox and.
...was for well first I was wondering if you
are gamer have become a gamer.
...and absolutely gamer...I remember when I
joined the company back in two thousand two within a month of the original xbox launch
...part of the whole recruiting is I got...were niceness.
And, yeah, I play I...xbox
...independent of all this I play a lot of xbox I'm
a fairly narrow gamer I only play...are the most recent called
...so I'm reasonably good but if you follow me
on xbox live my gamer spores...simply because first-person shooters typically don't reward
lots so my...my reputation is actually greater if you're in called duty...as opposed to
...broader...sharing your gamer tag today...it's with.
Yeah, I again recalling when you went to xbox everybody was thinking maybe because it I also
...musician I think you still...right and I was kinda curious if you're going to do something with xbox
music or if you got involved inI had nothing...the...
And, it again it was the...the reason I felons xbox was not because I was a...gamer
...always...to...it was...people right I met people on...
and then you'll once I was in the got it only got better right and,... the experiences I
...xbox...with all these people were so much smarter than me I just learned some
of the caspian that's an interesting point can-you talking all about things that
you learned doing the xbox operating system that you think are very much
applicable to these other platforms like other things xbox team was kind of
pushing the envelope on are doing that is benefitted now like phone in the surface hub
and poland's even that's an interesting question we certainly if I look at the
depends we made an xbox one which, you know, we're watching kind of like bear fruit
...the broader...you know.
Some people know...some people don't xbox one runs three operating system right
...right we basically buddha very minimal
hosed os right which runs the hyper visor and we launched the system all which is where
...apps run and then we have this very tuned partition another
vm we run the games we did that for a variety of reasons
what are the biggest reasons we did was we want to resource
...right because if you look at the consul?
Programming environment right you have this fixed function hardware that lives
for you multiple years.
...and developers are very used to having nothing else happening on the box right like when you
wrote xbox...sixty game it's as if we've effectively reboot the machine right there's not a lot
of other microsoft code running when you're playing...duty under three sixty.
So, we wanted to be able to give that kind of resource isolation guarantees and we look at the
tools...were available to us at the time and that was the most...do a which is basically use
...of ibm to go enforces if we look at things like in directives twelve
vertex well today which is on both xbox one is coming to xbox one incoming to windows
ten-x will ship with windows...you know, those same ideas of, you know,
having dedicated resource allocations that gain can predictably no I need this
page memory it's going-to be there for me no matter what else is happening on the box this is mine and
...stay...those ideas, you know,...kind of starting to see
you become more generalized that's probably the biggest, you know,
thing that happened in xbox...kind of see
...for...I remember when you guys first talked about the architecture
...the xbox one operating system when we started hearing about the virtualization...dave cutlery
been working on that it was suddenly like old waiters three operating systems on here pretty much
for yet I mean that that's not going to be the case another devices
...and load...now that I mean...that we use the verycoarse
grain tool right to enforce the resource boundaries and it was the right thing for the time on that
product?
In general model I think that we
have more knobs in tools we can go deploy using...fourth-graders
...I don't think is the general model right but it was great for xbox game, you know,
I we could not...build the product we not done yet but, I think,... as we go forward,
you know, being able to put more resource isolation in the os probably more promising thing and were singled out
direct as easy
...things are probably changed a lot to from when you started working on xbox to now
...in terms of what microsoft's relationship is with gamers and
game developers especially because I know...of the examples here they talked about a
...was that candy crush sagawas built using this new ios tool...
Just a few years ago you can't even imagine microsoft really having a conversation with
...it's I don't know I could.
Maybe work but I know so,
I...you're doing more around unity and you're doing a lot around bringing
gain developers into the fold what...however they want to come to the...
...it has...change the relationship like microsoft relationship with game developments in your.
It's a great question I think in general people happy to see the things we're doing you know,
the reaction to us really embracing unity has been really,
really strong the reaction to.
The work we're doing a directs twelve has been really...you know,
bring xbox live more broadly we're definitely,
you know, especially with this...this...this the windows and release, you know,
we're putting a lot of energy...an effort into making sure that game developers can succeeding can make money or
...right so, you know, I think in general is positive we get feedback
it's great the feedback is not always positive which is great otherwise you'd just be,
you know,...withering would be very active so not I think the...really well what do you think
...my craft...puzzled we did you think...mean I thought about it I found out
about it the same time everyone else...it blew my mind I mean it's fantastic and,
certainly in terms of having an asset
...touches many millions of people's lives it's a fantastic.
Have you tried the hollow...I have not...the...I tried it
in january when I was there for the windows...event and one of the things that gets try was
...presley amount of my...player and you probably fun...but I still fatherly cool
and interesting I think it's going to be interesting to see the whole new audience of
...developers customers that this brings to microsoft and how that fits in with other things
you're doing, yeah, I mean it's?
It's...obviously the tech is super advanced and,
the last time I used to which was a while back it's pretty mind-blowing...
It just...values everything else and the fact that you can ready universal windows app
and run-off hollow is fantastic a lot of the technology,
you know, is getting mixed up with the rest of the...actually pretty healthy ...
Okay, what else what else but of course merger the glove will be so much
...the glove is going to be amazing I concert while...
The...the new project see since I think we can...start...
Of what else do you feel like people it you you've been kind of
not able to speak publicly for a number...publicly to us I should say
...do you think we don't understand rightnow...being
the microsoft community about where you guys are going with the underlying platform the
...technology like what don't we quite get that you want us to get...you know,
...I read, you know, people's reactions to when we go off and do...these press things
...actually people mostly get...you know, we are no
...incredibly serious about...windows ten,
you know, is a massive investment for us it's a massive bad and we could not be more which I think is,
you know, it's exciting it's...is xbox one
was we basically went from nothing note from a hardware...too, you know,
having a product with...operating systems running on
...and...black friday all that this project is comparably exciting
in some ways more exciting because it's just like we're bringing...bringing...writing everything to
...here to make sure that...have a great system...it's really exciting?
Anywhere hence.
Code means anything you want to drop on the audience,
you know, you're usually good for...to besides...that is...the I guess,
you know, my problem is so again I don't do public stop credo heads down shipping the stuff that,
you know,
you know I've got the wall that's in front of you...to make sure accurately group that there's a lot of
...acceptance and time-out that we have...already disclose because, you know, we've made a lot of announcements...
Thanks done this is a great thank you but I have to ask a couple questions so,
I love watching you and...and,
leo's report on that show windows...is...it's all it's
that I watch that every everyone is just fantastic what...portability like he's a
really good guy actually is he like he sounds...yes he's totally like he sounds on the radio
...not a big microsoft's fan I know but,
we do our best to try to educate...keep...you know, we can give a free copy with
...could you...it that is within my affording...I've heard I've heard some people
get for free venture he would get better free copy.
I can...to lewd okay they'll...will tell because we're in a
...this week...thanks yet think it up.